<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_odds.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encoding Guidelines for the ELTeC</title>
            <author>Work Group 1</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft for discussion</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>A born digital document drafted in TEI format by LB</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-12-17">First (partial) discussion draft</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>This is the first draft of a reference document defining the encoding scheme to be used
            for the European Literary Text Collection (ELTeC) which will be a major deliverable of
            COST Action 16204, <title>Distant Reading</title>. As a first draft it necessarily
            contains much uncertainty, either because policies have to be determined, or because
            issues are under-specified. This version represents the views of its author only.
            Particular topics on which policy remains to be defined are signalled below with the
            label <q>Open Question</q>. </p>
         <div>
            <head>Principles</head>
            <p>The MoU for the project points out that <q>Distant Reading methods cover a wide range
                  of computational methods for literary text analysis, such as authorship
                  attribution, topic modelling, character network analysis, or stylistic
                  analysis.</q> The focus of the ELTeC encoding scheme is thus not to represent
               texts in all their original complexity of structure or appearance, but rather to
               facilitate a richer and better-informed distant reading than a transcription of its
               lexical content alone would permit. For example, it seems useful to distinguish
               headings and annotations from the rest of the text, and to be able to locate
               stretches of text within gross structural features such as chapters and paragraphs.
               It is probably also useful to distinguish passages belonging to different narrative
               levels (for example, direct speech versus narrative or quotation versus narrative)
               and to identify reference points such as page breaks. It is less useful to record
               exact nuances of rendition or spelling in a particular version of a text. Our goal is
               not to duplicate the work of scholarly editors or to produce (yet another) digital
               edition of a specific source document. </p>
            <p>In selecting features for inclusion in the markup scheme, we have been guided, but
               not limited, by existing practice as far as possible <note place="foot">Particular
                  collections we have examined are listed in section <ptr target="#sources"/></note>
               but the main goal has been to identify a small core set of essential textual features
               which can be readily (preferably automatically) identified in existing digital
               transcriptions, or easily and consistently provided by new transcriptions. </p>
            <p>This document lists all the textual features which are to be distinguished in an
               ELTeC conformant transcription. Whenever a given feature exists in a text, it will be
               marked up as indicated here. No other features will be captured by the markup: if
               some textual feature not provided for here is identified by a marked up source text,
               that markup will be removed. The goal is to ensure that the ELTeC texts can be
               processed by very simple minded (but XML-aware) systems primarily concerned with
               lexis and to make life easier for the developers of such systems. </p>
            <p>We make no attempt to propose markup for linguistic annotations here. The assumption
               is that this will be produced by different annotation systems in different ways,
               though with an association between such annotations and the basic lexical structures
               represented by the core ELTeC markup. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Basic Transcription Guidelines</head>
            <p>The basic unit of the ELTeC corpus is the text of a single novel, represented by a
               TEI <gi>text</gi> element. We propose no mechanism (other than metadata) to encode
               units larger than a single novel, such as multipart novel series like Proust's
                  <title>A la recherche du temps perdu</title> or Balzac's <title>Les
                  Rougon-Macquart</title>. </p>
            <p><label>Open Question</label> Should we include liminal matter (titlepages, prefaces,
               appendixes...) in our transcriptions? The following policies seem possible: <list>
                  <item>No : these typically belong to a particular edition or version of the text,
                     and should therefore systematically be excluded</item>
                  <item>Yes : these often form a significant part of the reader's experience (cf.
                     the foreword to most editions of <title>David Copperfield</title>). Mark them
                     up using <gi>front</gi> and <gi>back</gi> as appropriate.</item>
                  <item>Sort of : do not transcribe them, but indicate that they have been
                     suppressed by using the <gi>gap</gi> element. </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Within the body of a text, major structural divisions (parts, sections, chapters
               etc.) will be captured using the generic <gi>div</gi> element, with attributes
                  <att>type</att>, <att>xml:lang</att>, <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> used as
               further detailed below.</p>
            <p>The names used for hierarchic structural divisions of a novel above the chapter are
               arbitrary, culture-specific, and often inconsistent : in some novels things called
                  <q>part</q> contain things called <q>book</q> and in others the reverse. We
               propose to follow TEI in using a single element (<gi>div</gi>) for every hierarchical
               structural division, down to the level of <q>chapter</q>.</p>
            <p><label>Open Question</label> Is it useful to retain the name used for each level in
               the original source (the type of div) ? <list>
                  <item> Yes: it is easy to keep and may help referencing : use the <att>type</att>
                     attribute to hold the name used for each level of div in the work in
                     question</item>
                  <item>No : this name adds no useful information beyond the level indicated by the
                     XML structure </item>
                  <item>No : it would be more useful to provide an explicit and normalised
                     indication of the hierarchic level for the benefit of non-XML-aware processors
                     (e.g. <code>level1</code>, <code>level2</code> etc.)</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>The (human) language in which a text is expressed is indicated explicitly by the
                  <att>xml:lang</att> attribute which supplies the ISO 2 letter code for the
               language concerned. This attribute will always be supplied on the <gi>text</gi>
               element to specify a default, and may also appear on other elements, for example
                  <gi>foreign</gi>, to indicate passages where the language changes. The various
               different languages used in a given text will be itemized in its metadata (see
                  <gi>langUsage</gi> element in the header). </p>
            <p><label>Open question</label> Should passages exhibiting regional or dialectal
               variation be specially signalled? <list>
                  <item>No : this is too fine grained and controversial a distinction to be made
                     with reliable consistency </item>
                  <item>Yes : treat this in the same way as any other kind of code switching and
                     define a set of appropriate language codes for the project</item>
                  <item>Maybe : just use the <gi>distinct</gi> element to indicate the kind of
                     variation concerned</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>A single reference scheme will be defined for the whole corpus, with the following
               components: <list>
                  <item>text identifier : every text will have an identifier consisting of its two
                     letter language code and a three digit serial number, for example
                        <code>FR042</code></item>
                  <item>chapter identifier: each chapter or equivalent will have an identifier
                     concatenating the text identifier and a three digit serial number, for example
                        <code>FR042012</code> is the twelfth chapter of the 42nd French novel. </item>
                  <item>If sub-chapter segmentation (see below) is implemented, then the segments
                     will append a further four digit serial number.</item>
               </list>The identifier will be supplied as the value of an <att>xml:id</att> attribute
               on each <gi>text</gi>, <gi>div</gi> or <gi>s</gi> element as appropriate. Adding this
               identifier is an easily automated task which can be built into the workflow for
               accession to the ELTeC.</p>
            <p>Note that these identifiers will not necessarily correspond with the numbering used
               in a particular source text. In a work where the first twelve chapters are considered
               to form part one, and the next twelve constitute part two, the first chapter of the
               second part will have an identifier ending <code>013</code>, even though it may be
               numbered <code>1</code> in a source text. </p>
            <p><label>Open question</label> is it important to preserve the original numbering,
               particularly for deeply structured texts? <list>
                  <item>Yes : the original numbering is widely used to reference the text: it should
                     be supplied as using the <att>n</att> attribute on the <gi>div</gi>.</item>
                  <item>No : the original numbering and referencing scheme are of no use in our
                     intended applications, introduce unnecessary complexity, and may be a source of
                     confusion. </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>The chapters of a novel mostly consist of prose, arranged in paragraphs, for which we
               will use the TEI <gi>p</gi> element. It is not unusual to find other structures
               however, specifically verse, or passages of dialogue presented as if in a play, with
               speaker labels and even stage directions. Less frequently, novels may contain
               material presented in list or tabular formats. Graphics with their own associated
               heading or other text are also frequent. </p>
            <p><label>Open Question</label> how should material other than running prose and
               dialogue be encoded? <list type="ordered">
                  <item>Use the appropriate TEI elements for verse or drama (<gi>lg</gi>,
                     <gi>l</gi>, <gi>sp</gi>, <gi>stage</gi>)</item>
                  <item>Use the appropriate TEI elements for lists and tables (<gi>list</gi>,
                        <gi>label</gi>, <gi>item</gi>, <gi>table</gi>, <gi>cell</gi>,
                     <gi>row</gi>)</item>
                  <item>Use the appropriate TEI elements for embedded graphics (<gi>figure</gi>,
                        <gi>graphic</gi>, <gi>head</gi>)</item>
                  <item>Suppress all non-prose material, replacing it by <gi>gap</gi></item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Novels are also full of direct speech, represented using various different
               conventions, but almost always distinguished from the narrative voice. The first
               person narrative is also common, but may be regarded as a special case. How exactly
               different narrative strands are articulated in a novel, and the extent to which they
               may be characterised by their lexis has been a preoccupation of many <q>distant
                  reading</q> style analyses. It might therefore be helpful to distinguish material
               purporting to be direct speech from material purporting to be narrative in our basic
               encoding, though to do so consistently and accurately may occasionally be
               problematic.</p>
            <p><label>Open Question</label> Should passages presented as direct speech in a novel be
               distinguished from passages presented as narrative? <list>
                  <item>Yes : use <gi>q</gi> and avoid nesting problems by always nesting it within
                        <gi>p</gi></item>
                  <item>Yes : use a <gi>milestone</gi> to mark the beginning and end of each passage
                     of direct speech</item>
                  <item>Sort of : provide an attribute on <gi>p</gi> to indicate whether or not the
                     paragraph contains direct speech</item>
                  <item>No : rely on (or normalise) typographic conventions such as quote marks or
                     dashes to distinguish direct speech only. </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Printed texts typically deploy a number of conventions which can cause problems for
               linguistic analyses of even the most basic kind. Changes of font or style
               (italicization or use of superscript, for example) can have particular lexical
               significance which should be taken into account. End-of-line hyphenation can make it
               harder to identify the exact form of a token. Non-standard (i.e. non-modern)
               spellings can mislead parsers. Our proposed encoding aims above all for consistency
               and transparency in what is reliably achievable, leaving more difficult and
               problematic issues to be addressed by linguistic annotations. </p>
            <p>We do not preserve the lineation of running prose in our source texts, since this is
               always purely an artefact of the source edition. For the same reason we will
               reassemble words broken across a line break, silently removing any hyphen present.
               (This will make it impossible to use our texts for hyphenation studies. So be it.) </p>
            <p><label>Open Question</label> : Should page breaks in the source text be preserved ? <list>
                  <item>Yes : this is useful information (e.g. to determine words-per-page, or to
                     anchor links to an image of the source text) which is usually available at
                     no-cost in existing digital texts</item>
                  <item>No : the proposed uses don't justify the cost of providing the information
                     if it is missing. And pagination is inherently copy-specific.</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Font and style variations in the source text usually signal something. Italics may
               signal emphasis, quotation, foreign language terms etc. Superscripts almost always
               signal abbreviation. The visual salience of these variations is of considerably less
               interest to distant readers than the intended function they signal. However, it is
               not always easy to determine that function reliably and consistently by algorithm.
               Some simple cases could however be addressed. A possibly strategy is outlined below.
               It assumes the existence of a digital version of the text in which visual features
               are explicit, whether by means of TEI-style markup or styling information such as
               that provided by Word. <list>
                  <item>if possible, replace indications of highlighting by an appropriate TEI
                     element, chosen from the following list : <gi>foreign</gi>, <gi>title</gi>,
                        <gi>emph</gi></item>
                  <item>otherwise, replace all indications of highlighting by the TEI <gi>hi</gi>
                     element</item>
                  <item>indications of superscript characters (such as French
                        <soCalled>14&#x1d49;</soCalled>) should be removed. Instead, the TEI element
                        <gi>abbr</gi> should be used to indicate the presence of an abbreviated
                     word: <code>&lt;abbr>14e&lt;/abbr></code></item>
               </list></p>
            <p><label>Open Question</label>: Is it feasible or useful to recode highlighted spans of
               text in this way? <list>
                  <item>Yes : in many cases this can be an automatic process and the results justify
                     investing the effort </item>
                  <item>No : there are likely to be too many borderline or debatable cases to do
                     this automatically so this would have to be done as part of a major proof
                     reading exercise</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Whichever solution is adopted, it should be applied uniformly across the ELTeC. A
               collection in which some texts make distinctions ignored by others is
               unsatisfactory.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>TEI Elements used</head>
            <p>This section will provide a checklist of TEI elements used in the body of each ELTeC
               text, with descriptions and examples of their intended applications. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Metadata in the TEI Header</head>
            <p>This section will describe the metadata associated with each text (title, authorship,
               date etc.) The intention is to provide this in a standardised way to facilitate
               subsetting of the collection, using (for example) coded values for the descriptive
               selection criteria associated with the text. Although we are not aiming at fidelity
               to particular editions, it’s probably important to know from what kind of edition the
               transcription derives (e.g. first printed edition, authorized reprint, unknown
               edition) </p>
            <p>This will be encoded using the relevant elements proposed for the TEI Header. This
               section will provide a checklist of all TEI Header elements to be provided for each
               text, with descriptions and examples of their intended usage. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Linguistic annotation</head>
            <p> Later stages of the project will need to use additional markup facilities to
               represent more sophisticated annotations: these will form an additional layer, not
               discussed here: the principle should however be that the base text we provide is
               always available in a uniform encoding.</p>
            <!-- <p rend="color(#009933)">To include further preparation steps in our suggestion, would
               maybe be desirable (e.g., if the “base text” is somewhat difficult to process).</p>
            <p rend="color(#009933)">Further questions/aspects concerning “the base text” might be:
               covering special character encoding, language encoding within the text (e.g. English
               In German texts), token definition, documentation of the overall characteristics of
               the base text (kind of transcription guidelines – what can be expected)</p>
            <p rend="color(#009933)">Do we need to consider an additional normalization of the
               texts? I would assume that for automatic processing would require text with as little
               as possible linguistic variants. </p>
-->
         </div>
         <div><head>Formal specification</head>
            <p>The ELTeC encoding scheme defined by this document is  a TEI-conformant
               customization, from which user documentation, and formal RELAXNG or DTD specifications can be
               generated automatically. This section contains the schema specification itself.</p>
            <schemaSpec ident="ELTeC">
               <moduleRef key="tei"/>
               <moduleRef key="core" include="head item l lg list p pb sp stage hi"/>
               <moduleRef key="textstructure" include="div body"/>
               <moduleRef key="header"/>
            </schemaSpec>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back xml:id="sources">
         <p>Sources consulted</p>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl>An introduction to TEI Simple Print 
               <idno type="URI">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-exemplars/html/tei_simplePrint.doc.html</idno></bibl>
            <bibl>Burnard (Lou) <date>2005</date>
               <title level="a">Metadata for corpus work</title> in <title>Developing Linguistic
                  Corpora: A guide to good practice</title> ed. Martin Wynne. Oxford: Oxbow Books,
               pp 30-46. <!--<ref target="2005-metadata.xml">XML source</ref>--></bibl>
            <bibl> Odebrecht, Carolin. (2017). Metadata for Historical Corpora. Realization of the Metamodel for Corpus Metadata with the help of TEI Customization [Data set]. Zenodo. http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.267999</bibl>
            <bibl><idno type="URI">github.com/cligs/textbox</idno></bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
