<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_odds.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encoding Guidelines for the ELTEC</title>
            <author>Work Group 1</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft for discussion</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Original document drafted in TEI format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>First draft on ES </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>

      <body>
         <p>This document is the first draft of a reference document defining the encoding scheme to
            be used for the European Language T E Corpus (ELTEC) which will be a major deliverable
            of COST Action 125404, <title>Distant Reading</title>. As a first draft it necessarily
            contains much uncertainty, either because policies have to be determined, or because
            issues are under-specified. This version represents the views of its author only.
            Particular areas of uncertainty are signalled. </p>

         <div>
            <head>Principles</head>
            <p>The purpose of the ELTEC encoding scheme is not to represent the original text in all
               its complexity of structure or appearance, but to facilitate a richer and
               better-informed distant reading than a transcription of its lexical content alone
               would permit. For example, it seems useful to distinguish headings and annotations
               from the rest of the text, and to be able to locate stretches of text within gross
               structural features such as chapters and paragraphs. It is probably also useful to
               distinguish passages belonging to different narrative levels (for example, direct
               speech versus narrative or quotation versus narrative) and to identify reference
               points such as page breaks. In selecting features for inclusion in the markup scheme,
               we have been guided, but not limited, by existing practice as far as possible <note
                  place="foot">Particular collections we have examined are listed in section <ptr
                     target="#sources"/></note></p>
            <p>This document lists all the textual features which are to be distinguished in an
               ElTec conformant transcription. Whenever a given feature exists in a text, it will be
               marked up as indicated here. No other features will be captured by the markup: if
               some textual feature not provided for here is identified by a marked up source text,
               that markup will be removed. The goal is to ensure that the Eltec texts can be
               processed by very simple minded (though XML aware) systems primarily concerned with
               lexis. </p>
            <p>We make no attempt to propose markup for linguistic annotations here. The assumption
               is that this will be produced by different annotation systems in different ways,
               though with an association between such annotations and the basic lexical structures
               represented by the Eltec markup. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Basic Transcription Guidelines</head>
            <p>The basic unit of the Eltec corpus is the text of a single novel, represented by a
               TEI <gi>text</gi> element. We propose no mechanism (other than metadata) to encode
               units larger than a single novel, such as multipart novel series like Proust's
                  <title>A la recherche du temps perdu</title> or Balzac's <title>Les
                  Rougon-Macquart</title>. </p>
            <p><label>Open Question</label> Should we include liminal matter (titlepages, prefaces,
               appendixes...) in our transcriptions? The following policies seem possible: <list>
                  <item>No : these typically belong to a particular edition or version of the text,
                     and should therefore systematically be excluded</item>
                  <item>Yes : these often form a significant part of the reader's experience (cf.
                     the foreword to most editions of <title>David Copperfield</title>). Mark them
                     up using <gi>front</gi> and <gi>back</gi> as appropriate.</item>
                  <item>Sort of : do not transcribe them, but indicate that they have been
                     suppressed by using the <gi>gap</gi> element. </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Within the body of a text, major structural divisions (parts, sections,
               chapters etc.) will be captured using the generic <gi>div</gi> element, using its
               <att>type</att> attribute as necessary (a closed set of values needs to be defined)</p> 
            <p>The (human) language in which a text is expressed will be indicated explicitly by
               using the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute to supply the ISO 2 letter code for the
               language concerned. This attribute will always be supplied on the <gi>text</gi>
               element to specify a default, and may also appear on other elements, for example
                  <gi>foreign</gi>, to indicate passages where the language changes. The languages
               used in a given text will be itemized in its metadata. </p>
            <p><label>Open question</label> Should passages exhibiting for example regional or
               dialectal variation be specially signalled? <list>
                  <item>No : this is too fine grained and controversial a distinction to be made
                     with reliable consistency </item>
                  <item>Yes : treat this in the same way as any other kind of code switching and
                     define a set of appropriate language codes for the project</item>
                  <item>Maybe : just use the <gi>distinct</gi> element to indicate the kind of
                     variation concerned</item>
               </list></p>
<p>A single referencing scheme will be defined for the whole corpus, with the following components:
<list>
   <item>text identifier : every text will have an identifier consisting of its two letter language code
   and a three digit serial number, for example <code>FR042</code></item><item>chapter identifier: each chapter
      or equivalent will have an identifier concatenating the text identifier and a three digit serial number,
      for example <code>FR042012</code> is the twelfth chapter of the 42nd French novel. </item>
   <item>If sub-chapter segmentation (see below) is implemented, then the segments will append a further four digit serial number.l
   will </item>
</list>The identifier will be supplied as the value of an <att>xml:id</att> attribute on each <gi>text</gi>, 
   <gi>div</gi> or <gi>s</gi> element as appropriate.</p><p>Note that these identifiers will not necessarily
   correspond with the numbering used in a particular source text. In a work where the first twelve chapters
   are considered to form part one, and the next twelve constitute part two, the first chapter of the second
   part will have an identifier ending <code>013</code>, even though it may be numbered <code>1</code> in a
   source text. </p><p><label>Open question</label> : is it important to preserve original number of 
   deeply structured texts?
   <list>
      <item>Yes : the original numbering is widely used to reference the text: it should be supplied as
      using the <att>n</att> attribute on the <gi>div</gi>. In the preceding example, the  value of "1" for this
         attribute and the <gi>div</gi> element containing the twelve chaoters making up oart two will have the
         value "2" for this attribute.  </item>
   </list></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>TEI Elements used</head>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Metadata in the TEI Header</head>
            <p>Metadata associated with each text (title, authorship, date etc.) should always be
               represented in a standardised way to facilitate subsetting of the corpus. This will
               also include coded values for selection/descriptive criteria itemized above.</p>
            <p>Although we are not aiming at fidelity to particular editions, it’s probably
               important to know from what kind of edition the transcription derives (e.g. first
               printed edition, authorized reprint, unknown edition) </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Linguistic annotation</head>
            <p> Later stages of the project will need to use additional markup facilities to
               represent more sophisticated annotations: these will form an additional layer, not
               discussed here: the principle should however be that the base text we provide is
               always available in a uniform encoding.</p>
            <!-- <p rend="color(#009933)">To include further preparation steps in our suggestion, would
               maybe be desirable (e.g., if the “base text” is somewhat difficult to process).</p>
            <p rend="color(#009933)">Further questions/aspects concerning “the base text” might be:
               covering special character encoding, language encoding within the text (e.g. English
               In German texts), token definition, documentation of the overall characteristics of
               the base text (kind of transcription guidelines – what can be expected)</p>
            <p rend="color(#009933)">Do we need to consider an additional normalization of the
               texts? I would assume that for automatic processing would require text with as little
               as possible linguistic variants. </p>
-->
         </div>
         <div>
            <schemaSpec ident="eltec">
               <moduleRef key="tei"/>
               <moduleRef key="core" include="head item l lg list p pb sp stage hi"/>
               <moduleRef key="textstructure" include="div body"/>
               <moduleRef key="header"/>
            </schemaSpec>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back xml:id="sources">
         <listBibl>
            <bibl><idno type="URI">github.com/cligs/textbox</idno></bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
