<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>WG1: Sampling criteria for ELTeC</title>
                <author>carolin</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-12-11</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2017-12-15T11:52:44Z</date><name>lou</name>converted to TEI</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Cost Action CA16204 – WG1 </head>
            <head>Sampling criteria for ELTeC</head>
            <head>Outline</head>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Task</item>
                <item>Method</item>
                <item>Representativeness</item>
                <item>Requirements of sampling criteria</item>
                <item>Criteria</item>
                <item>Metadata for texts in ELTeC</item>
                <item>Literature</item>
            </list>
            <div>
                <head> Task </head>
                <p>The task for WG1 is to develop guidelines for data and metadata for the creation
                    of the ELTeC. This task can be split up into several distinct tasks: Guidelines
                    for corpus design, metadata scheme and annotations. This discussion paper
                    focuses on corpus design and metadata because both tasks interplay with each
                    other.</p>
                <p>The CA16204 has the goal to create a big benchmark corpus of literature from
                    1850-1920 (first period) for different computational distant reading methods for
                    corpus annotation and analysis. The task of creating annotation guidelines of
                    WG1 needs to be closely communicated and coordinated with WG2 in order to know
                    which methods and tools needs which kind(s) of annotation model and format. The
                    same holds for the development of the metadata scheme. </p>
                <p>For creating such a benchmark corpus, we need a corpus design which allows for a
                    comparability of texts and individual sub-collections according to different
                    metadata set(s). It should be possible for every COST Action member to sample
                    sub-collections from the ELTeC for specific tasks and research questions. In a
                    first step, we focus on the development of clear, operationalizable, transparent
                    and motivated selection criteria for the corpus.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Method</head>

                <p>First, I would like to discuss whether the task of corpus building requires
                    normative selection criteria (canon) or methodical selection criteria (corpus
                    sampling). The first and foremost important difference between the approaches is
                    the motivation of criteria. A canon is the portrait of someone’s prestigious
                    social, cultural, economic status and it reflects a normative self-promotional
                    legitimation and rating decisions. In contrast, corpus design follows a research
                    question or context and is therefore more research goal oriented. A second
                    important difference is the way of considering the actual texts. Canons and
                    corpus design rely on different text definitions and interpretations. As Moisl
                    (2009: 876) puts it ‘Data is ontologically different from the world.’ Canons
                    select texts to be included. By texts, the canons may consider the
                    manifestation, the extension or the work of a text (cf. IFLA 2009). A canon can
                    contain an extension of a certain text which is available in different languages
                    and prints. Ontologically, these different levels of text are different to what
                    a text in a corpus might be (cf. van Zundert and Andrews 2017). This means, that
                    digitization is a kind of annotation, hence interpretation (Odebrecht et al
                    2017). A representation of a text in a corpus (e.g. transcriptions, OCR) is the
                    result of interpretation. A corpus design needs to consider this for sampling
                    and digitization issues. </p>
                <p>At the end of the Action, ELTeC should contain literary texts (novels) from a
                    distinct period and from several languages. For each language (and thus for each
                    cultural contexts) there exists a diversity of canons which reflect different
                    prestigious groups such as publishers, authors and readers. These actors and
                    there possible influence on canon building is multi-relational. Each canon is a
                    result of rating texts from different perspectives. The rating can reflect
                    intellectual rating (a text is a representative of a certain literature period,
                    is influencing, is important), by economical rating (a text is published in more
                    than one print run), or by readers rating (a text is most popular by a certain
                    reader group) (cf. Hermann 2011 or Winko 1996). All these ratings can change
                    over time and may also interplay which each other. A canon can therefore reflect
                    different interpretation of ‘famous’, ‘important’ or ‘influential’ texts. These
                    criteria are not overall comparable. For example, texts from a smaller language
                    such as Czech are less likely to be highly reprinted in a way English texts from
                    the same period and genre are. Additionally, the awareness level of texts
                    depends on the influence of the country and their publishing houses.</p>
                <p>The criteria derived from a canon are not completely comparable and categorical.
                    Which prestigious group’s canon shall be considered which shall be excluded and
                    why? Are their comparable canons for novels in all countries of the language in
                    question? Algee-Hewitt and McGurl (2015) show an approach of a corpus design
                    based on several canons and what kind of problems occur. Each analysis of the
                    corpus than only shows the different effects of the decisions made by the
                    normative canon group. Considering national canons is also very difficult and
                    somewhat problematic. An example is the German National Canon of literature
                    which was developed in the 18 <hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi> century and was promoted by the national educational system until
                    the 1990. After the German reunification, the educational system does not
                    promote a strict canon and does not recommend a list of book to be read in
                    school or at university (cf. Winko 1996). Thus, taking such types of canons as
                    part of a sampling base of ELTeC would mean to reflect a political and social
                    past of German education and politics. Choosing between canons can then mean
                    choosing between tastes of (current) literature (in past and present) and tastes
                    of past literature when the canon builder rates historical texts. Finally, these
                    canons are not built to be the sampling guidelines for a corpus which we would
                    like to build in the Action.</p>
                <p>The MoU of CA16204 formulates the goal as follows: “The main aim and objective of
                    the Action is to This Action will develop the resources and methods necessary to
                    change the way European literary history is written.” This goal requires a new
                    approach of corpus design, metadata design and annotation models. As Fowler
                    (2002, 214) puts it: ‘The current canon sets limits to our understanding of
                    literature, in several ways’. Relying on canons will oppose to the Action’s goal
                    in a fundamental way. Canons provide traditional and normative access to the
                    history of literature. In contrast, the Action focuses on new approaches to tell
                    another story. </p>
                <p>Therefore, I argue for a non-normative but metadata-based approach of sampling
                    criteria which will follow a corpus design approach. Corpus sampling criteria
                    are mostly oriented/developed by the research question or/and contexts of the
                    corpus creators group. In CA16204, we have no distinct research question nor a
                    fixed and previously known corpus creator group. The research context of the
                    Action is more interested in knowledge production in a methodological sense and
                    does not prefer a single method, model or theory. Furthermore, the member group
                    of the Action will fluctuate and consist of researches from different
                    disciplines with different theoretical and cultural contexts. Thus, we need to
                    build the corpus design on a methodical basis. With these method, we will also
                    be able to select canonical texts as well but not exclusively. <seg> </seg></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Representativeness and balance</head>
                <p>Additional to the aspect of ‘prestige’ (canon), the aspect of representativeness
                    is problematic for corpus design. Developing criteria for corpus design means to
                    decide which kind of sample of the world shall be included in the data base.
                    Obviously, including the whole population of literature of the 19<hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">
                        century of several languages is impossible. So we need to make a compromise
                        between what we would like to have in the corpus (all literature) and what
                        we can put in the corpus (sample).</hi>
                </p>
                <quote>It is a truism that there is no such thing as a ‘good’ or a ‘bad’ corpus,
                    because how a corpus is designed depends on what kind of corpus it is and how it
                    is going to be used. (Hunston 2008, 155)</quote>
                <p>Following Hunston (2008), a corpus design needs to follow the research goal. For
                    the Action, representativeness may be the relationship between the corpus and
                    the body of literature in question. ‘Representativeness refers to the extent to
                    which a sample includes the full range of variability in a population’ (Biber
                    1993, 243). To say something about the representativeness of a corpus requires
                    knowledge about the whole population of literature (in the period in qeustion).
                    Actually, we don’t know every book of every language published/read/discussed in
                    the period in question. It is further ‘impossible to identify a complete list of
                    ‘categories’ that would exhaustively account for all texts produced in a given
                    language’, (Hunston 2008, 161) or context. Such categories can refer to various
                    factors such as characteristics of authors, e.g., gender or place of birth,
                    publishers, topics of the texts, readership etc. Against the background of canon
                    building, there is also ‘no true measure of the ‘significance’ of a type of
                    discourse to a community’. The chance, that a corpus represents the whole
                    population of something increases with the size of a corpus. In this way, size
                    and representativeness are connected. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See Biber (1993) and Hunston (2008) for a detailed
                            discussion.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>Representativeness is therefore a kind of ideal which we would like to pursuit
                    but which cannot not achieved as whole. In line with the MoU, the ELTeC can be
                    designed as a monitor corpus where texts (from different languages and periods)
                    can be added over time. </p>
                <p>Balance refers to the internal proportion of the corpus. According the MoU, the
                    corpus shall contain 2,500 full-texts novels at least in 10 different
                    languages:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Languages: Dutch, English, French, German, Greek, Italian, Polish,
                        Portuguese, Russian, Spanish (ELTeC core)</item>
                    <item>1<hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">st</hi> iteration: 6
                        subcollections (100 novels per language) 1850 to 1920 starting with British,
                        French, Spanish, German, Greek, Polish</item>
                    <item>2<hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">nd</hi> iteration: 4
                        subcollections (100 novels per language) 1850 to 1920</item>
                    <item>3<hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">rd</hi> iteration: 6
                        subcollections in additional languages and subcollections for all 16
                        languages 1780-1850, </item>
                </list>
                <p>In this way, ELTeC is balanced with respect to language. With respect to genre,
                    the corpus is not balanced, all texts in the corpus shall be full novels. With
                    respect to time, the corpus design shall focus on the period 1850 to 1920. A
                    fully balanced corpus is an ideal which we only can try to achieve next to the
                    ideal of representativeness (Hunston 2008, 163). Balancing a corpus with respect
                    to gender can mean either that we chose the same amount of novels from each
                    gender or/and that we chose the same amount of words for each gender (if we can
                    determine the gender of every author and those using pseudonyms). To achieve
                    both balances it nearly impossible. So we have to decide which categories shall
                    be present in a balanced way in the corpus. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Requirements of sampling criteria</head>
                <p>According to the MoU, the corpus design should be balanced with respect to
                    language and publication date of the texts. This means not that the corpus
                    should be solely based on chronological criteria, meaning that we need a text
                    from each year of the period in question. The main sampling criterion ‘language’
                    will require not to include translations at all. The electronical availability
                    should not be a leading sampling criterion. But, availability is a limiting
                    factor. A text should not be excluded from ELTeC because it is not digitized,
                    but it should be excluded if the text cannot be made freely available in ELTeC.
                    If we only use availability as a selecting criterion, we are at risk of copying
                    projects such as ‘Gutenberg’ for German historical texts. We then need
                    additional criteria which can be applied without having to know (read) the texts
                    in question. The criteria should be checked without a deep knowledge about the
                    texts. Otherwise, this will oppose the goal of the whole Action and the
                    methodical approach of distant reading. The criteria should be
                    operationalizable, meaning decidable from text metadata. Here, we define text
                    metadata in a wider scope than only the classical bibliographical metadata. In
                    this way corpus design interacts with metadata. Some of the text’s metadata can
                    be used a sampling criteria. These criteria are text-external and -internal
                    criteria (cf. Hunston 2008) on which we then need to rely on. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Criteria</head>
                <p>In this section, we provide the sampling criteria for ELTeC. Overall, ELTeC
                    should contain fictions – printed novels – no translations. </p>
                <p>Authors should write in their first language?</p>
                <p>Authors should be located in Europe?</p>
                <p>Feeling, that it is somewhat not the most important issue which distinct novel is
                    in the corpus as we have no curation approach, no thematic predominance due to
                    research question etc.</p>
                <p> Implementing a member vote when having a preselection?</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Date<list type="unordered">
                            <item>1850 to 1920 (first iterations)</item>
                            <item>text sample covering each decade in the period</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Language of the text<list type="unordered">
                            <item>Dutch, English, French, German, Greek, Italian, Polish,
                                Portuguese, Russian, Spanish</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Author<list type="unordered">
                            <item>male, female, (undefined)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Length<list type="unordered">
                            <item>Average (cf. balancing) </item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Kind of novel<list type="unordered">
                            <item>Main theme (cf. Falkentheorie)</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list></div>
                <div>
                    <head>Metadata for texts in ELTeC</head>
               
                <p>For every text in the ELTeC, the following metadata should be recorded. </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>title</item>
                    <item>subtitle</item>
                    <item>publication date</item>
                    <item>publication place</item>
                    <item>publisher</item>
                    <item>series</item>
                    <item>editor</item>
                    <item>author<list type="unordered">
                            <item>name</item>
                            <item>sex</item>
                            <item>first language</item>
                            <item>place of birth</item>
                            <item>entry of a person database such as GND if available</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>size<list type="unordered">
                            <item>in words / in tokens</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>pages</item>
                    <item>topics (cf. Falkentheorie)<list type="unordered">
                            <item>politics, crime, espionage, provincial, school, adventure, war,
                                faith, domestic, nature, factory </item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>subgenre<list type="unordered">
                            <item>work-in-progress novel</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Narrator<list type="unordered">
                            <item>first person</item>
                            <item>third person</item>
                            <item>authorial narrator</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>canonicity/reception<list type="unordered">
                            <item>rated by a canon: y/n</item>
                            <item>canon</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>keywords<list type="unordered">
                            <item>from OPACs? others? Own?</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>language<list type="unordered">
                            <item>possible: language area, language type (e.g. German,
                                Bavarian)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Source reference (if available)<list type="unordered">
                            <item>e.g. DTA, textgrid etc.</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Literature</head>

                <p><hi rend="bold">Algee-Hewitt, Mark; McGurl, Mark </hi>(2015): Between Canon and
                    Corpus. Seix Perspectives on the 20th-Centurary Novels. Literary Lab. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Biber, Douglas </hi>(1993): Representativeness in Corpus Design.
                    In: <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing </hi>(8), 243–257.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Herrmann, Leonhard</hi> (2011): System? Kanon? Epoche? In:
                    Matthias Beilein, Claudia Stockinger und Simone Winko (Hg.): Kanon, Wertung und
                    Vermittlung. Literatur in der Wissensgesellschaft. Berlin: De Gruyter (Studien
                    und Texte zur Sozialgeschichte der Literatur, Bd. 129), S. 59–75.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hunston</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Susan</hi> (2008): Collection
                    strategies and design decisions. In: Anke Lüdeling und Merja Kytö (Hg.): Corpus
                    Linguistics. An International Handbook. 2 Bände. Berlin: De Gruyter (1), S.
                    154–168.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">IFLA</hi> (2009): Functional Requirements for Bibliographic
                    Records (Technical Report). Online verfügbar unter
                    http://www.ifla.org/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records,
                    zuletzt geprüft am 23.12.2016.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lüdeling</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Anke</hi> (2011): Corpora in
                    Linguistics. Sampling and Annotation. In: Karl Grandin (Hg.): Going Digital.
                    Evolutionary and Revolutionary Aspects of Digitization. New York: Science
                    History Publications (Nobel Symposium, 147), 220–243.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Moisl, Hermann</hi> (2009): Exploratory Multivariate Analysis.
                    In: Anke Lüdeling und Merja Kytö (Hg.): Corpus Linguistics. An International
                    Handbook. 2 Bände. Berlin: De Gruyter (2), S. 874–899.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Winko, Simone</hi> (1996): Literarische Wertung und Kanonbildung.
                    In: Grundzüge der Literaturwissenschaft. Hrsg. v. H. L. Arnold und H. Detering.
                    München, 585–600.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">van Zundert, Joris; Andrews, Tara L.</hi> (2017): Qu'est-ce qu'un
                    texte numérique? A new rationale for the digital representation of text. In: <hi
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities </hi>(32), S. 78–88.
                    DOI: 10.1093/llc/fqx039.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
